Hello,
I'm going to be talking about Pericarp and showing some examples of
how this library
that I wrote fairly quickly works and how you can use it and also
going through its code
and then showing a few examples that I put
together that use Pericarp but also use some
techniques that should be familiar to you if you've been paying
attention and if you haven't you can go back and look at some
of the other tutorials around event listeners and around doing
things with setting the current time of time-based media objects.
So here's a GitHub repository for Pericarp and it's a fairly
simple library and I don't think we've really talked about like,
oh,
what's a library,
what's a framework,
what's an app,
it's a tool.
Generally library has like reusable functions in it
and that's what this is and
you know when
you're getting started out as a programmer,
as somebody doing creative code,
it's not always clear like,
oh,
when do I need a function?
When do I need to, when do I need
a class?
When do I need to like spend time thinking about
the structure of something that I'm trying to build?
And I think the best time to do that is when
things are starting to feel too complicated.
So let me just go through the description here,
lightweight tool for hooking things to timestamp ranges
and HTML5 audio or video.
Inspired by functions in popcorn.js,
I use the most.
A Pericarp is the tough outer shell of a popcorn kernel.
I mean, it's a general term for
the outside of any fruit really,
but it's crucial for the popping process and it
can get stuck in your teeth and also in your guts.
So Pericarp.cue is a
function,
the
main function to use Pericarp and it takes a few arguments.
The first one is the DOM object being targeted.
So if you, you know,
see down here like let video equals document query select your video,
which loads a reference to the video DOM object
into into this variable video.
Video is an example of what you would
send to the first argument of Pericarp.
You can also use a CSS selector string
like video with quotes around it,
which will send the first video element in the DOM that it finds.
I added some flexibility to that.
Similarly,
the start and end time,
which you can measure in seconds or hours,
minutes and seconds separated by colons and surrounded
by quotes or just minutes and seconds with the
colon in between with quotes because it's a string,
right?
JavaScript isn't going to know if you take
a couple numbers and put a colon in between,
it's going to just
get really confused.
And then you pass a function
to do when it's in between the start time and the end time,
it's like when it's in this band that you've selected,
do something.
Do it once.
When it enters, do it every time it enters that,
that time period.
Then optionally,
kind of a clean up function that you
can run and leaving that time span.
You don't always,
you're not always going to need that,
but it's nice to be able to,
like if you're going to show something when
you're in between three seconds and five seconds,
it's nice to be able to say,
like let's hide that
when we leave.
So there's some example code here.
It's got popcorn emoji.
It's on a full program.
But it does kind of show how it might be used.
I'm going to actually walk through the code of the library itself.
It's quite short.
108,
11 lines.
A lot of that is stuff I didn't need to do,
but it makes it a little easier to use.
So I'm making an object here called Pericarp,
lowercase p.
And it holds an array in it with the cues.
These are here.
So you can open up your dev tools when
you're doing something with Pericarp.
You type pericarp.q's and then you can use square brackets,
zero to load the first one,
one,
two,
three,
as just sort of a diagnostic tool.
Then I've got some helper functions here.
So you can pericarp.2hms,
not her majesty's ship.
You know, like the, like a
boat talk, right?
I was minute seconds.
So it'll take,
you know,
1500 seconds and convert that into,
however many hours,
minutes,
and seconds that is.
Similarly, the other way around.
If you have a string,
that is hours, minutes, and seconds,
to sec will convert it into
just seconds,
which is what most,
most of the function,
seconds, and JavaScript just want seconds.
But it's easier to think
in the kind of, like,
time periods that the video tag actually shows us.
When we use it,
it shows us minutes and hours,
minutes and seconds.
So you can kind of
walk through the function,
just,
you know,
it does some testing to make sure that,
oh,
there is no hours on here.
We don't need to multiply by that.
Then q is where the
good stuff happens.
Starts to,
and this takes the element,
the start time,
the end time,
the start function,
and the end function.
It does some testing to make sure, oh,
if element is a string and not a,
actually an HTML element,
then I will run a query selector with that
string and see if that returns an HTML element.
So that's, that's what's going on here.
Then we make sure it's audio or video,
like
one tag or the other.
We want to make sure that the end
time isn't less than the start time because that will mess things up.
We want to make sure that the functions are functions.
We want to make sure that the numbers are numbers.
And so,
you know,
out of 111 lines,
a lot of them is just testing stuff that,
you know, if you use it right,
these things aren't ever going to fire,
but they will also let you know when you do it wrong.
And that's handy and worth doing.
So then it makes.
I have this.
It's basically a class,
pericarp,
and the constructor is the function
below without being called a constructor.
You know, I actually need the keyword.
For those of you who have used classes,
it's just JavaScript is the way it is.
So it makes this new object and pushes it to the array
of cues that you can then access in your dev tools.
Then we've got this object here.
We have the same arguments.
And again, it does some testing.
Make sure that things are the right kind of thing.
And then it sets its own properties
to some of the incoming arguments.
It makes sure that it,
like,
if there isn't an end function set,
it makes an empty one so that rather than being nothing,
it's a function because you want it to be a function.
Otherwise, this code won't work.
So we have a status variable here that's used internally.
The tracks weather,
weather we've entered,
but not yet exited the time frame that's specified.
And this event listener is where all that work happens.
We add an event listener to time update for every pericarp object.
For every time this function is called,
it's adding a new event listener that's listening to time update.
So you have multiple event listeners.
It's on the same event.
And that's okay.
It's good that the language supports that because if
every time you add it a time update event listener,
it overwrote the previous one.
We couldn't really do this without, like,
having
a ton of if statements.
That would be really hard to follow.
So I'm grateful that it's structured the way it is
in the language.
So this is basically saying, if the video or our
audio element here,
if the elements current time is greater than our cues start,
and the current time is less than the cues end time,
which is like,
we're in between these goal posts.
And the cue hasn't already started.
Then let's say it started and let's run that function.
This started status thing here is to make sure that the start function
isn't getting called every time time update runs multiple times.
That's for a second.
If that's what you want,
you want something that's just going to loop and
run over and over again.
You could just do that with your own time update listener.
Then if it's at any other time,
so it's like outside of the
frame we've specified,
then this started gets set to false.
We've left the time span.
And we can run the end function.
Which if you haven't passed one,
we'll just be this empty function,
which is fine.
I have some thoughts about other things we could do down here.
And then I've got one more helper function down here,
just to test whether numbers are numbers.
Copy and pasted that from stack stack overflow.
That is how things work sometimes.
So how does this work out in the wild?
Do the motion study first.
So here's an example where we have multiple time based elements.
This is a video.
These are the same video.
I don't have the controls turned on.
I can turn them on.
They won't be all that helpful.
I have them off because I don't really want these to be interactive.
Because I'm controlling them with this audio element.
This audio element is playing a song.
The young marble giants Zebra Trucks
from 1980. This sound closed down.
I'm in my heart because there was a radio station I grew up in the
broadcaster range of where they did this thing called radio chat room.
And they just opened phone lines.
And this music would be playing in the background.
And you could have a conversation with
somebody that you never met on the radio.
And so the people who were the hosts of the radio show,
they didn't say anything.
They were just sort of curate who was talking.
And it was kind of blew my mind.
My young media brain was blown away
that you could even do that with radio.
So what's going to happen is I hit play here.
The song is going to start when the synth and
the bass kick in an organ actually not a synth.
This
Moe bridge motion study,
which is only a second long,
will start playing.
And every time it loops.
This Moe bridge motion study,
the same video will advance basically one frame.
I did do some math to figure out how many fractions
of a second corresponded to a visible frame change.
And I seem to have lined it up.
Okay.
These are images that go back to the prehistory of cinema
back to the Zuo praxiscope that Edward Moe bridge innovated
in order to win a bet with Lee Lydon Stanford about whether
it was like all of the horses legs off the
ground or on the ground at the same time.
It runs off the ground, I think.
So yeah, let's do that.
Oh,
and every time this one loops,
it speeds up a little bit.
And so there's something here about like
the continuity of time and animation.
And there's some interesting research about who's depicted here.
Some of the jockeys that Moe bridge photograph are known.
And some of them aren't this one.
This one.
The one for this.
Any G. We know the name of the horse.
We don't know.
We know the name of the jockey.
And that's one of the ways in which the history
of technology is also deeply racialized.
So let's go.
It gets faster and faster.
You can see I didn't like having the
controls on because this play button here.
Kind of distracting,
but you can see the way that the loop works.
Gradually moves across.
And then resets.
And this gets so fast.
You start seeing all the legs at once.
It looks like an eight-legged horse.
And the continuity here,
emotion becomes smoother and smoother and smoother.
And yeah, this looks wild over here.
Anyway, it gets to the end of the song.
The
organ and the bass drop off.
And this one stops.
And then
the song loops when they kick in again,
it starts again.
So what does that look like in code?
This is some vestigil CSS. There's no video container in this.
So never mind that.
There's a video.
There's audio.
I said the video to 300 pixels wide.
The audio to 600 pixels wide.
So it's like,
that's why it took up the space of two videos.
I'm using site and details to do the stuff below the videos.
I've got two videos here.
One of them has the ID fast.
One of them has the ID slow.
They point at the same asset on the internet archive.
And then I have this radio chat room loop
that's loading from my, my own domain.
Then this descriptive text down here.
I've got a block quote from,
Rebecca Solnitz River of Shadows,
which is a wonderful book about Edward
Moibrid and early California history.
What distinguishes a technological world
is that the terms of nature are obscured.
One need not live quite in the present or the local.
Some other stuff here with links.
And the code is,
you want 89 to 109?
It's like
20 lines of code.
We set our DOM.
We set our variables to point at the different DOM objects.
And then I call pericarp.q.
We're running on the audio.
And then from 8.3 seconds to 1 minute 29 seconds.
0.69.
I actually went into audacity to just move the playhead to get
very precise time code of like where certain things happened.
And you can see I'm using two different kinds of time code here.
8.3 seconds.
And then this string.
They both work.
This is also how I was testing my code, right?
So in between those times,
fast should start playing.
That's our main loop on the left.
And then when it leaves those timestamps,
fast should pause and the playback rate should reset.
Then I've got an event listener on fast that checks
for seek and seek happens when the loop resets.
So when it goes,
scrolling back up to the top here,
we see both these videos.
They, but
I have controls on the audio,
the control audio loops.
I don't have controls on the video.
The fast loops
and slow doesn't.
I actually
kind of loop it manually.
And you'll see how I do that.
So when fast has looped,
when it goes from the end of the video to the beginning,
this event fires.
I had to look up like,
how do you detect when I HTML5 element
with loop setting has actually done that.
And I found somebody had figured that out.
So basically, I'm like adding
slow dot current time.
Plus this, this is basically 0
.066 seconds was like the equivalent of moving one.
One frame in the zero praxis scope.
And that took some trial and error to find.
So
we're going to try and set the current time
to what it is plus that.
But if, if that target
will then make us longer than that video's duration,
then we're going to set.
We're going to set it to zero.
So this is just a variable that's
holding sort of the target current time.
And then every time,
you know,
this event listener is like tracking when the loop has occurred.
So then we add
0.06 to the playback rate
of fast.
And we set.
Slow's current time to the target.
So this is both.
On every loop, increasing the speed of fast.
And increasing
the current time of slow,
which is actually never playing.
Like that video is not playing.
We're just.
Moving the current time,
gradually through the timeline.
So we have three time elements here.
Audio is controlling fast.
Fast is controlling slow.
I did get some questions from like,
oh,
like,
how would this work with multiple elements?
You store them in different variables like like this.
And you keep track of,
you know,
and you use those variables to
get one to talk to the next.
It's actually pretty simple.
One more example.
And I hope you're using my new table of contents code to like
only listen to the parts of this that you want to.
So this is running on an.
An educational film called the growth of plants.
And it takes up most of the full screen.
What's going on in this is like another.
Example of like doing stuff.
You know, you know, I'm going to.
Using time update,
like using time events to do different things.
One of them, we make an image appear over here.
I've kind of a.
Stock image of like a like a star with arms.
The playhead will jump around a bit.
It will pause and make some text visible.
And then it's going to loop and constantly
get slower and slower and slower.
When you start about like a plant getting pollinated.
And then after a certain amount of times,
it will
proceed through the video.
We're not going to watch the whole thing in this demo,
but just giving you a heads up.
Like what goes on here?
Three seconds.
It should jump.
Now we're 24 seconds in.
We have a nice little star here.
That's like,
oh,
we could use that to make any image up here over a video.
Now the video is paused at five minutes in after another jump.
And it says the video is going to loop showing
slowing down each time until it reaches one quarter.
So you're speed below zero 0.25 playback rate.
You get no sound.
So these are kind of my boundaries.
Then the video will continue at its regular rate.
Press play to proceed.
So let this run a couple times.
It is very probable that some of the pollen grains
carried by the B will be brushed upon the stigma.
And thus fertilization will be brought about.
So it just gets gradually slower and slower.
I was kind of thinking about Martin Arnold's films where he's
like scrubbing back and forth of like this particular scene.
And you can't really do backwards video.
Because of the way that video is encoded,
you really need special kinds of frames.
And it's just not what browser video is meant for.
You could do this in a more specialized tool.
But kind of like,
you know,
you can't really do that. It's like a looping and slowing down.
It kind of draws attention.
It draws it out.
We'll look through the code real quick.
This one does use this video container.
I'm sorry.
Sometimes it's like I'm copying and
pasting stuff to make these examples.
And I didn't end up using it in the motion study.
But I did use it here.
And so border box means that
the width of the border is not added to the width of the box model.
If you're going to be doing much design.
HTML,
getting a sense of how the box model works is important.
Otherwise,
it'll be something that just confuses you ever once in a while. But,
you know,
you have to pick your battles here.
One of the things I do is make overflow hidden.
So if anything goes outside of this video container,
it's not going to make scroll bars.
We set the video to absolute position.
It's top left,
full width, full height.
The star is a
fixed position measured from the top and left.
And I'm using opacity on a lot of these elements
because we can transition opacity and it will animate
so you can fade things in and fade things out.
I'm also using mixed blend mode.
Those of you that have used Photoshop or Gimp,
like layers have these different blend modes.
And you can also use those in CSS. They
give you a lot of kind of imaging options.
And in this case,
the star image as I had it had this solid
black background and by using lightning,
the light in rather blend mode that just kind of disappears.
It's one of the reasons you can kind of
see through the star too didn't bother me.
And then I've got this text div.
The one that kind of said,
like,
hey,
I'm paused.
Here's what's going to happen.
I positioned that from the right and the top.
I said it's with,
I said a transparent that's only
a transition.
It's like a translucent,
it's like black and half,
half opaque
with white text.
So inside our video container,
we've got our single video,
the growth of plants.
I don't have a year on this video.
It doesn't actually say on the film.
And it's not in the metadata that came
from the can when they scanned it.
We have our star.
It has an ID to make it a little bit easier
to target in case I had multiple images.
And then we have the star image.
Then we've got our empty text div here.
As usual,
I set some variables to point at DOM objects.
I'm doing something that I've done a couple times here in
the script of like only showing the video when it can play.
And so here's this wait for video function.
You don't really need this,
especially if script is at the bottom of the page,
but it works.
So here's some documentation for pericarp.
So we have pericarp.q.
We're targeting the video
between 12 seconds and 22 seconds.
The opacity actually drops to 30% on the video.
So it kind of grays out.
We didn't actually see that happen because we didn't,
the playhead was never between 12 or 22. It jumped over it.
It's like we're playing pitfall and we swam over the pit.
All right.
We swung on the vine over the tree.
We're the pit.
That's an ancient video game
for you kids.
And you can see here, like
what I'm passing to the start function and the end function of
like what to do when you enter this time span and leave the time
span are these nameless functions that I just pass as arguments.
And that's a pattern that we see a lot in JavaScript.
And it's can be a little bit confusing.
Like,
well,
we're going to see what we're going to do. What are all these functions?
Well, it's just like, I need a function.
This one doesn't have a name.
It doesn't need a name.
It's just going to live here and do its thing.
Then between three seconds and 3.5,
it will jump us to 24 seconds.
That's like
getting us
beyond this span.
Then from 30 to 31,
it takes us to almost five minutes.
So it jumps again.
At five minutes,
I tell a video to pause,
change the text content on that div
and then set it to opacity to one.
So it fades up over the course of one second,
because that's what the transition set at.
And then you see this text.
I could have actually just had the text in the div.
But this doing it this way means I can change the text
and use that div for different text at different times.
But depending on what you want to do, you might
want to just preset those.
And
hide one, show another.
There isn't really a right way to do this stuff.
Then I have this loop that's constantly slowing down.
Between five minutes,
11 seconds and five minutes,
13 seconds.
So if the playback rate is greater than quarter speed,
reduce the playback rate by 0.1.
And then
set the current time to 505. So it goes from 505,
gets to 501,
jumps back to 505. That's kind of this loop that's happening.
And every time it gets to 511,
it slows down.
But if the playback rate
is less than 0.25,
or equal to 0.25,
it's going to be a little bit more.
Then the playback rate is set back to normal.
And the loop doesn't happen.
And we leave
this time span.
Then and these power-car functions are not in chronological order.
If you're writing your own program,
you might want to do that.
Because being organized will help
you keep track of what's going on.
Between 25 and 35 seconds,
it's doing show stuff.
So here's an example of not using a nameless function.
Instead,
actually passing an existing function to a pair of cart.
And you just notice you do not add the parentheses when you
pass an existing function as the arguments of another function.
And you might ask,
well,
what if I need arguments on that?
Well,
you have to just find another way.
Anyway, that's a good thing.
How that works.
There's a lot of other things you could do with this.
And I hope to see some of you do that.
Probably the best way to use the pair of
cart code is to download the JavaScript file,
include it in your directory,
and just include this line here.
And if you run into issues,
feel free to open a ticket or just get in
touch with me the way you normally would.
Anyway, long, long video.
Very rambly.
Sorry about that.
But hopefully this is useful to you.
Have a good one.